subtitles: OSiRiS CC-BY-SA, English Translation by María Verónica Di Genno
Gcoop presents
cooperative codes
Computer programs have permeated our life,
that is to say, software
Software is the name given to an idea or to a collection of ideas that let the operation of machinery
cell phones, cameras, planes, and traffic lights.
Today, people's ideas which make machines function are sold everywhere.
Actually, here we can see an average human being
in this case, a woman.
She's sending a text message through her phone.
She's just purchased proprietary software to print some ideas as instructed by her boss.
She should be happy.
But, how can someone pack an idea in a box and be able to sell it?
An idea is a form or an aspect that occurres to somebody.
That is to say, it's something immaterial.
To be able to show an idea and to offer it, it's necessary to make it material.
We illustrate it with a drawing of this light bulb next to our friend
the Average Woman
The light bulb is an invention that Thomas Alva Edison patented in 1880.
But the idea had already been put forward by Humphry Davy
and previously, by Warren De La Rue.
That is to say, Edison patented an idea that took various forms starting from the exchange of knowledge.
It isn't necessary for an idea to turn into something palpable to become a material object.
Far back in time, humans developed language,
which is the matter that allows them to represent their ideas.
Language enables humans to relate in a different way with nature in comparison to the way animals do it.
Language permits culture to exist,
that is to say, all this exchange of ideas enables man to interact and cooperate in a community
The Average Woman belongs to the western culture.
In the origin of this culture, people used to exchange their ideas within assemblies and public open spaces.
Unfortunately, today public spaces have bars
and ideas cannot be exchanged so freely.
Let's see.
For software to be able to be a material object, somebody must have thought an idea and have written it.
That is to say, software is a script.
The ones who write the ideas that become software are called developers or programmers.
Acturally, here we have a programmer.
At this moment, the good old programmer is developing an idea by using the script,
but in a strange language that only machines can understand...
and the programmers
This strange language is also written in a computer
and it is arranged in a certain way so as to have the machine do what one wants it to do.
We call those scripts Source Code.
The good old programmer has had the idea of developing a different colour light bulb,
completely free.
Like an idea that travels through language,
programs have the possibility of being copied, reinterpreted,
added, reinvented and transmitted again.
To depirve software of its collective spirit is to deprive humans of the exchange of ideas,
that is to say, to deprive them of their culture.
It's like putting a light bulb behind a window
or to lock up a person in a public square.
But, let's talk to a specialist who can explain these ideas to us.
This is a specialist.
Proprietary software basically differs from free software on freedom conferred to the users.
Free software allows the user
to learn from the program, modify it...
redistribute it, whereas proprietary software can only let people use it with some restrictions.
and it is always tied to the company that created it
Thank you, specialist.
But, how did we get to the proprietary software?
Very simple.
Proprietary software companies take the good old programmer's idea and hide the "source code."
They take the most restrictive form under the laws of intelectual property that they indeed have them promulgated:
"All rights reserved."
This way, the only thing that our friend can hopefully do is to use the program.
Here there is a samll trap.
Intelectual property
is fundamentally based on the idea that an author is that person who creates an original unprecedented work.
However, the word "author" comes from the Latin word "auctor",
which, in turn, comes from "augere": which means increase, to advance.
That is to say, an author doesn't invent anything
they only improve something that already existed.
In 1883, world leaders sign the Paris Convention,
which legally recognizes intelectual property and allows export of ideas.
Of course, in 1883 software was not as we know it today.
Let's talk to another specialist in order for him to update us.
Software is born with computers in the 50s.
Software transforms into a commodity and it starts to be limited in such a way as not to be
... an available element say as public knowlegde can be.
on the basis of letting increasingly monopolistic companies to develop.
Uh-huh... But what does that mean on the good old programmer daily basis?
There is a constant reduction in the cost of development,
It is said that from the price of software, about 5% is
what the programmer indeed earns
whereas the owner of the product receives the rest who has in some way
the ownership of the source code, of that intelectual property.
Crystal clear.
That is to say: if the good old programmer worked for a transnational proprietary software company
he/she would only earn the 5% of what it costs to pack his/her idea and sell it.
Our Average Woman has been a victim of advertising and she has wanted this package.
Let's see how she is doing.
She's installing her proprietary software and she seems happy.
Argh! It has what you call a pretty environment image.
Oh Oh, it seems that something doesn't work well.
The package didn't say that the printer wasn't compatible with the program.
She'll have to buy another printer.
Her boss has demanded her ideas in order for the company, where she works, be able to continue profiting.
Now it seems that she will be able to print her ideas and take them to her boss.
Oops, it seems that something doesn't work well.
The antivirus needs another update to scan the new printer.
That is to say, she needs to buy another proprietary software and to pay for another license.
Do not worry, friend.
We know that almost everything is horrible, but not all software is proprietary,
and not all companies aim at stamping out your money.
The good old programmer hasn't been hired by a transnational,
he decided to organise a free software cooperative.
In a cooperative, the members meet to cooperate.
To cooperate is to act jointly with others for a common goal.
This is a cooperative.
The good old programmer says that a for-profit enterprise is organised in a hierarchical way
and the decisions are taken by the capitalist.
On the other hand, a cooperative is organized in a horizontal way and each member represents a vote.
That is to say, decisions are taken in assembly.
The development model of a proprietary software company is closed,
the organizational structure is pyramidal,
it depends on a boss, "those who can't do, teach"
Basically, the one who has to do the tasks,
the workers,
work in a rush, because everything has to be done for tomorrow or for yesterday
they are the last ones to find out about changes.It happens the same to our friend.
On the contrary, cooperative model garanties equal participation in decision making and doing the work.
And this is the best model in line with free software development.
By the way, how is work organized in a cooperative?
This specialist can help us.
Generally speaking, in the capitalist system we have two kinds of companies,
limited liability companies and partnerships,
in the particular case of cooperatives, like work cooperatives where I belong to
it's an enterprise, where the worker finds work for themselves
and work leads and it's subordinated to capital, in liability companies it's the other way around.
Crystal clear.
Now, since you're a specialist, could you sum up the origin of capital and capitalism in twenty seconds?
No..., indeed, I couldn't...
Ok, it's alright, we'll have to do it.
Capitalism is the economic and political system which has got two main elements:
capital (the resources that are available to produce something) and the capitalist (possesses the resources and earns the profit).
But a worker is also necessary.
The Average Woman or a programmer are typical examples of a worker.
Our friend, due to the company where she works, she's already undermining her co-workers jobs.
Most of the people in the world haven't got goods to sell in the market and make a profit.
That's why what they sell is their work force.
Work force is the capacity of every person to produce something.
A person sells it for some hours, the capitalist gives them money.
We call that money salary.
In the salary, the capitalist saves part of what costs the work force and keeps the money for himself.
That saving is called profit or exploitation of workers.
The Average Woman, who is a worker and had to buy her program from a for-profit enterprise,
has part of her salary taken away
and she has spent part of her salary in buying proprietary software,
a new printer and, besides, she'll have to buy another antivirus software.
Let's ask another specialist if he agrees with our summary about capitalism.
Mmmmmm....
Excellent. Now, tell us, how does cooperativism appear in Argentina?
At the end of the XIX century, there is a big immigration in the nation and those immigrants find out that they have got
absolutely nothing, nor where to go.
And they started to outline different forms of organising among themselves,
so as to give a hand to each other in everything that they needed,
in such a way that, the first cooperative organizations
started to appear in the nation.
Thank you, specialist.
Many times, cooperatives are out of our sight.
Hey, psst, psst, not there!
Correct, there.
There are different ways of classifing cooperatives.
Among them, we find the work cooperatives,
which are associations of people gathered with the aim of improving their social and economical situation.
In a work cooperative of free software there are workers who think of ideas and develop their culture.
But, how does a cooperative work daily?
Let's talk with a member of gcoop
This is a member.
A memeber is a person who works jointly with other people to develop an activity,
whether it be business, social, or cultural.
We don't sell little boxes, nor we sell licenses, but...
... we sell the sevicies associated with software, that is the adaptation, the implementation...
and the training to use a specific software that solves a problem of an organization.
We get paid, for the associated services, for our work,
that is to say we get paid once and we do the job once,
in the other model you do the job once, and you get paid for ever.
Let's ask the programmer
why people think that they can have bigger problems
using free software than using proprietary software.
There are no software that hasn't got mistakes
the difference is that regarding proprietary software,
one doesn't see the mistakes and there is a whole marketing campaign that says "this one works, it works perfectly."
In free software, we are open-minded and we say "these are the mistakes, we'll correct them."
By the way, how can free software help our friend with her problem?
Well, she can hire a programmer to solve that problem,
here is where I do my part, modifying...
...the program so it does what my friend needs it to do. It's in line with the social economic model.
What do you mean?
Free software is social economy,
because it creates local jobs and, as a result, money of the nation stays in the nation.
Self-management has the power of taking decisions as opposed to what, some time ago, used to be incumbent on the owners of companies.
Boss,#**#*** I resign.
Well done, friend.
And no fear for your decisions,
the software cooperatives of the nation...
have gathered in the Argentine Federation Cooperatives of Work of Technology, Innovation and Knowledge
(FACTTIC)
and they'll never leave you alone.
Using software should become a more conscious act.
Companies that sell ideas justify their prices by making us believe that software is a huge industry.
And our friend has already proved that it's only about the packaging of free ideas.
Proprietary software is based on the original idea that cannot be copied.
Originality doesn't exist.
Humanity exists...
and humanity, as far as we know...
it feeds itself on culture and advances due to culture by exchanges and rewrites.
Our friend has learned that every software is free by itself...
and, if she wants to print and spread freely her ideas
she can do it better and more affordable through it.
But she knows more.
She has learned that working in a collective and pleasant manner brings benefits
not only economical, but also social for the rest of humankind
Our friend is no longer an average human being and she's becoming...
a model cooperativist.
END
sharing is good! translate the subtitles into another language